<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>SSO on Uitsmijter</title><link>/tags/sso/</link><description>Recent content in SSO on Uitsmijter</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Uitsmijter 2023.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 18:38:37 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/sso/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>SSO for Grafana: Because Nobody Likes Remembering Another Password</title><link>/articles/2025-12-15_grafana-sso-uitsmijter/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/articles/2025-12-15_grafana-sso-uitsmijter/</guid><description>&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re reading this, you probably already know what Grafana is, but let&amp;rsquo;s get everyone on the same page: &lt;strong>Grafana&lt;/strong> is your friendly neighborhood observability platform. It&amp;rsquo;s the thing that turns your messy metrics, logs, and traces into beautiful dashboards that actually make sense. You know those colorful graphs your DevOps team stares at during incidents? Yeah, that&amp;rsquo;s Grafana. It&amp;rsquo;s like having a command center for your infrastructure—except instead of launching missiles, you&amp;rsquo;re launching alerts about your CPU usage hitting 99%.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Built Cloud-Native from Day One: Why We Rewrote SSO from Scratch</title><link>/articles/2025-11-27_kubernetes-tenant-status/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/articles/2025-11-27_kubernetes-tenant-status/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="why-we-built-this-from-scratch" class="heading">Why We Built This from Scratch &lt;a href="#why-we-built-this-from-scratch" aria-labelledby="why-we-built-this-from-scratch">
&lt;!-- &lt;i class="fas fa-link anchor">&lt;/i> -->
 &lt;svg class="svg-inline--fa fas fa-link anchor" fill="currentColor" aria-hidden="true" role="img" viewBox="0 0 640 512">&lt;use href="#fas-link">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Here&amp;rsquo;s something unusual: after decades in IT and software development, you learn one cardinal rule: &lt;strong>don&amp;rsquo;t reinvent the wheel&lt;/strong>. Use existing solutions. Stand on the shoulders of giants. Build with proven libraries and frameworks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So why did we build an SSO server from the ground up?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Because when we looked at the landscape of existing solutions, we couldn&amp;rsquo;t find what we needed. Every option we evaluated was designed in the pre-CNCF era, before Kubernetes became the infrastructure standard, before GitOps workflows, before the cloud-native patterns we now expect from production systems.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>