<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Uitsmijter Articles on Uitsmijter</title><link>/</link><description>Recent content in Uitsmijter Articles on Uitsmijter</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Uitsmijter 2023.</copyright><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>SSO for Grafana: Because Nobody Likes Remembering Another Password</title><link>/articles/2025-12-15_grafana-sso-uitsmijter/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/articles/2025-12-15_grafana-sso-uitsmijter/</guid><description>&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re reading this, you probably already know what Grafana is, but let&amp;rsquo;s get everyone on the same page: &lt;strong>Grafana&lt;/strong> is your friendly neighborhood observability platform. It&amp;rsquo;s the thing that turns your messy metrics, logs, and traces into beautiful dashboards that actually make sense. You know those colorful graphs your DevOps team stares at during incidents? Yeah, that&amp;rsquo;s Grafana. It&amp;rsquo;s like having a command center for your infrastructure—except instead of launching missiles, you&amp;rsquo;re launching alerts about your CPU usage hitting 99%.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Uitsmijter 0.10.3: Dynamic Scope Assignment</title><link>/articles/release-0.10.3-scope-enrichment/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/articles/release-0.10.3-scope-enrichment/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="uitsmijter-0103-dynamic-scope-assignment" class="heading">Uitsmijter 0.10.3: Dynamic Scope Assignment &lt;a href="#uitsmijter-0103-dynamic-scope-assignment" aria-labelledby="uitsmijter-0103-dynamic-scope-assignment">
&lt;!-- &lt;i class="fas fa-link anchor">&lt;/i> -->
 &lt;svg class="svg-inline--fa fas fa-link anchor" fill="currentColor" aria-hidden="true" role="img" viewBox="0 0 640 512">&lt;use href="#fas-link">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a>&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Imagine you&amp;rsquo;re managing a software development platform with hundreds of users across different teams. Some users are project managers who need to view reports and manage team assignments. Others are developers who need to commit code and create issues. Your authentication system knows exactly who has permission to do what, stored in your user database or calculated from group memberships. But here&amp;rsquo;s the problem: how do you get that information into the OAuth tokens your applications use for authorization?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Built Cloud-Native from Day One: Why We Rewrote SSO from Scratch</title><link>/articles/2025-11-27_kubernetes-tenant-status/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/articles/2025-11-27_kubernetes-tenant-status/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="why-we-built-this-from-scratch" class="heading">Why We Built This from Scratch &lt;a href="#why-we-built-this-from-scratch" aria-labelledby="why-we-built-this-from-scratch">
&lt;!-- &lt;i class="fas fa-link anchor">&lt;/i> -->
 &lt;svg class="svg-inline--fa fas fa-link anchor" fill="currentColor" aria-hidden="true" role="img" viewBox="0 0 640 512">&lt;use href="#fas-link">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Here&amp;rsquo;s something unusual: after decades in IT and software development, you learn one cardinal rule: &lt;strong>don&amp;rsquo;t reinvent the wheel&lt;/strong>. Use existing solutions. Stand on the shoulders of giants. Build with proven libraries and frameworks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So why did we build an SSO server from the ground up?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Because when we looked at the landscape of existing solutions, we couldn&amp;rsquo;t find what we needed. Every option we evaluated was designed in the pre-CNCF era, before Kubernetes became the infrastructure standard, before GitOps workflows, before the cloud-native patterns we now expect from production systems.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>From One to Many: Understanding JWT Signing as You Scale</title><link>/articles/2025-11-24_jwt-signing-algorithms-guide/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/articles/2025-11-24_jwt-signing-algorithms-guide/</guid><description>&lt;p>Let me tell you a story about Bread and Butter Inc., a small e-commerce startup that learned about JWT signing the hard way—so you don&amp;rsquo;t have to.&lt;/p>

&lt;h2 id="the-beginning-building-bread-and-butter-inc" class="heading">The Beginning: Building Bread and Butter Inc. &lt;a href="#the-beginning-building-bread-and-butter-inc" aria-labelledby="the-beginning-building-bread-and-butter-inc">
&lt;!-- &lt;i class="fas fa-link anchor">&lt;/i> -->
 &lt;svg class="svg-inline--fa fas fa-link anchor" fill="currentColor" aria-hidden="true" role="img" viewBox="0 0 640 512">&lt;use href="#fas-link">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Sarah and her team of three developers are building Bread and Butter Inc., an online marketplace for artisan goods. They need authentication—users should log in once and access both the website and the mobile app without entering their password again.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Uitsmijter 0.10: Enterprise-Grade JWT Signing with JWKS Support</title><link>/articles/2025-11-08_uitsmijter-0-10-jwks-rs256/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/articles/2025-11-08_uitsmijter-0-10-jwks-rs256/</guid><description>&lt;p>One of the most requested features for production deployments is finally here: &lt;strong>JSON Web Key Set (JWKS) support with RS256 asymmetric signing&lt;/strong>. Uitsmijter 0.10 brings enterprise-grade JWT token management that scales seamlessly with Kubernetes horizontal pod autoscaling, includes automatic key rotation, and provides a zero-downtime migration path from HS256.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re running Uitsmijter in production—especially in a microservices architecture or multi-tenant environment—this release fundamentally changes how you manage JWT security.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Uitsmijter 0.10.0: Foundation for the Future</title><link>/articles/2025-10-27_uitsmijter-0-10-roadmap/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/articles/2025-10-27_uitsmijter-0-10-roadmap/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="uitsmijter-0100-foundation-for-the-future" class="heading">Uitsmijter 0.10.0: Foundation for the Future &lt;a href="#uitsmijter-0100-foundation-for-the-future" aria-labelledby="uitsmijter-0100-foundation-for-the-future">
&lt;!-- &lt;i class="fas fa-link anchor">&lt;/i> -->
 &lt;svg class="svg-inline--fa fas fa-link anchor" fill="currentColor" aria-hidden="true" role="img" viewBox="0 0 640 512">&lt;use href="#fas-link">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a>&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>We&amp;rsquo;re excited to announce Uitsmijter 0.10.0 - a release that lays the groundwork for powerful new capabilities. Over the past month, we&amp;rsquo;ve modernized our entire codebase, implemented highly requested features, and prepared the architecture to support advanced authentication and authorization features.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>

&lt;h2 id="building-on-solid-ground" class="heading">Building on Solid Ground &lt;a href="#building-on-solid-ground" aria-labelledby="building-on-solid-ground">
&lt;!-- &lt;i class="fas fa-link anchor">&lt;/i> -->
 &lt;svg class="svg-inline--fa fas fa-link anchor" fill="currentColor" aria-hidden="true" role="img" viewBox="0 0 640 512">&lt;use href="#fas-link">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This release represents a significant milestone in Uitsmijter&amp;rsquo;s evolution. We&amp;rsquo;ve invested heavily in modernizing the foundation - migrating to Swift 6.2, refactoring for scalability, and implementing production-ready infrastructure.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Version 0.9.6</title><link>/articles/2024-11-01_version_0.9.6/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/articles/2024-11-01_version_0.9.6/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="uitsmijter-096-release-new-features-improvements-and-fixes" class="heading">Uitsmijter 0.9.6 Release: New Features, Improvements, and Fixes &lt;a href="#uitsmijter-096-release-new-features-improvements-and-fixes" aria-labelledby="uitsmijter-096-release-new-features-improvements-and-fixes">
&lt;!-- &lt;i class="fas fa-link anchor">&lt;/i> -->
 &lt;svg class="svg-inline--fa fas fa-link anchor" fill="currentColor" aria-hidden="true" role="img" viewBox="0 0 640 512">&lt;use href="#fas-link">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We’re excited to announce Uitsmijter version 0.9.6, packed with feature additions, enhancements, fixes, and important
updates. With this release, we’re pushing Uitsmijter forward with improved performance, better tooling, and
compatibility enhancements.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We&amp;rsquo;ve made a significant step forward on the &lt;a href="https://discourse.uitsmijter.io/t/uitsmijter-roadmap-0-9-6/20">roadmap&lt;/a>,
streamlining and enhancing the developer experience with several key updates, new features and some fixes.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Making it easier for new developers to get started with open source projects</title><link>/articles/2024-03-06_code/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/articles/2024-03-06_code/</guid><description>&lt;p>Open source projects are like a vast field that offers developers a wealth of
opportunities to get involved and work together on exciting projects. Beyond the purely
social aspect, participation in such projects offers a wide range of benefits. Not only
can developers acquire new skills and contribute to the community, but they can also
customize the software and optimize it to their own needs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Helping to shape the code according to one&amp;rsquo;s own ideas is an incentive for many,
especially when it comes to use within a company. By adding new features, fixing bugs
and optimizing performance, the software can be customized to meet the exact requirements
needed without having to reinvent everything. This flexibility gives developers the
opportunity to implement creative ideas and design the software in a unique way. It
becomes easier to realize your own project ideas.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Empowering digitisation through shared data, experiences, and procedures.</title><link>/articles/2023-12-13_empowering_digitisation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/articles/2023-12-13_empowering_digitisation/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="navigating-digital-transformation-overcoming-legacy-challenges-for-smes" class="heading">Navigating Digital Transformation: Overcoming Legacy Challenges for SMEs &lt;a href="#navigating-digital-transformation-overcoming-legacy-challenges-for-smes" aria-labelledby="navigating-digital-transformation-overcoming-legacy-challenges-for-smes">
&lt;!-- &lt;i class="fas fa-link anchor">&lt;/i> -->
 &lt;svg class="svg-inline--fa fas fa-link anchor" fill="currentColor" aria-hidden="true" role="img" viewBox="0 0 640 512">&lt;use href="#fas-link">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In an era of rapid technological evolution, digitisation has become the cornerstone of progress, albeit at varying paces
across different regions. Germany for example, often viewed as an economic powerhouse, is navigating the digital landscape
at a measured slow pace. The challenges faced by small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) in the wake of the second wave
of digitisation are particularly notable. We explores the imperative need for flexible authorisation systems and the
hurdles posed by legacy applications in the ongoing digitization journey of SMEs.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Migrating a monolith application into microservices with single sign on</title><link>/articles/2023-11-17_monolith/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/articles/2023-11-17_monolith/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="general-discussion" class="heading">General Discussion &lt;a href="#general-discussion" aria-labelledby="general-discussion">
&lt;!-- &lt;i class="fas fa-link anchor">&lt;/i> -->
 &lt;svg class="svg-inline--fa fas fa-link anchor" fill="currentColor" aria-hidden="true" role="img" viewBox="0 0 640 512">&lt;use href="#fas-link">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>

&lt;h3 id="the-path-to-microservices-a-journey-of-innovation-and-empowerment" class="heading">The Path to Microservices: A Journey of Innovation and Empowerment &lt;a href="#the-path-to-microservices-a-journey-of-innovation-and-empowerment" aria-labelledby="the-path-to-microservices-a-journey-of-innovation-and-empowerment">
&lt;!-- &lt;i class="fas fa-link anchor">&lt;/i> -->
 &lt;svg class="svg-inline--fa fas fa-link anchor" fill="currentColor" aria-hidden="true" role="img" viewBox="0 0 640 512">&lt;use href="#fas-link">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In today&amp;rsquo;s fast-paced tech landscape, companies are continually seeking innovative ways to stay competitive and meet
evolving customer demands. One of the most profound shifts capturing the attention of forward-thinking organizations is
the transition from monolithic applications to microservices architecture transformation that revolutionizes the very
core of software development, deployment, and maintenance, offering compelling reasons to embrace the future.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Welcome to Uitsmijter.</title><link>/articles/first/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/articles/first/</guid><description>&lt;p>This blog is super fresh and launched today. Please come back later and subscribe to our
&lt;a href="/index.xml">RSS-feed&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While we are writing remarkable articles, you can also check out other resources:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://uitsmijter.io">Our Website&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://docs.uitsmijter.io">Documentation&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://github.com/uitsmijter">Github Organisation&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://discourse.uitsmijter.io">Forum&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>See you soon.
Kris from Uitsmijter&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>